[Music]
thank you foreign
number 108 I think it's great to be back
with you all and today science is back
on the menu after after a long time
we're doing science again
uh so before I greet you all I would
like to tell you that this is a
sponsored video and today's sponsors are
today's sponsor is the like button so go
ahead and hit the like button smash it
if you want to please our sponsor
right let's say who all is here with us
I can see debashish pranjal kuldeep Juna
parth Ravi sahil chaitanya Ashish Azar
Aryan
Aditi shweta Manish
trolls of bwl crazy Johan
shreyas akshit bhavya Lord Mountain
historica
Aditya and lots of other people who did
bought gaming Tushar yo bro yubraj
Rajesh Sunil Etc Great to be back with
you all
so we're doing science today we are
going to talk about science and I have
as always taken a whole lot of questions
and let's see how many I can answer
so with that said let's go to question
number one
on this brand new science episode
the first question is by GP
uh the question is what advice do you
have for people to tell science apart
from pseudoscience yeah this is a good
question it's an important question and
this is a question that uh kind of
upsets a lot of people when I answer it
because you know uh first of all we have
to understand the difference between
science and philosophy
also between science and religion and
spirituality and then about science and
pseudoscience and when we talk about
religion especially people get really
upset
so let me try and explain this and since
people get upset I have kind of written
it down I had written some notes a long
time ago like a couple of years ago I'm
gonna share them with you and I'm gonna
read this out so that uh
you get a better understanding so it's
like this first let's understand the
difference between science and
philosophy so science as well as
philosophy deals with theories and
models of the universe even philosophies
about this science is concerned with the
nature of the universe the nature of
reality philosophy is also concerned
with the nature of the universe but also
it is concerned about the role of human
beings in the universe so philosophy is
concerned with the nature of reality and
the meaning and the purpose of existence
right science relies only on empirical
data and empirical knowledge data that
can be observed and replicated knowledge
that can be tested philosophy is not
constrained by this requirement of only
dealing with
empirical leader and knowledge
philosophy is also about a priori
knowledge not that is independent form
experience for example intuition right
science is about physical objects only
philosophy is also about physical
objects but it's also about abstract
objects ideas
abstractions such as God the soul
morality ethics and so on scientific
theories must be predictive they must be
able to make testable and falsifiable
predictions philosophical theories need
not be predictive or testable or
falsifiable
so scientific theories must be
falsifiable philosophical theories need
not be falsifiable they can be
completely speculative in nature
philosophy does not carry the burden of
needing to be falsifiable
so string theory is an idea is an
example it is not falsifiable Multiverse
theories are also not falsifiable
therefore they belong in the realm of
philosophy now religion and spirituality
are all about belief I mean when we talk
about religion we are mainly talking
about abrahamic religions because when
you talk about dharmic religions there
is a whole lot of philosophy in it which
has a lot of logic and it's not only
about belief but typically and we don't
even know what spirituality is so there
is no real definition of spirituality
everybody isn't has their own definition
so religion and spirituality are vague
they are mainly about belief it is
enough to have a belief a belief is
enough it is valid when it comes to
religion and spirituality
even if when it comes to Supernatural
things and places things that have no
place in science right so religions are
belief systems and beliefs in religion
are valid even they even if they are
completely against the principles of
Science testibility and all that right
so that is about a philosophy versus
science and also about religion now
there is more to this obviously right
that's not the only thing uh so when it
comes to pseudoscience now so the
majority of the people who get into
pseudoscience are people who don't have
scientific training and the people who
kind of mix up science in in the
religion or science and faith in science
and spirituality for instance there are
a lot of people who talk about Quantum
healing and Quantum this and Quantum
that and whatever right
quantum mechanics has nothing to do with
healing or or spirituality or anything
but they kind of mix these things up so
that is pseudoscience right so so it's
people who are well meaning
and who
here a little bit or read something a
little bit about something about science
or quantum mechanics and they mix things
up and these are the quantum mechanics
uh supports whatever their claims are
right so
pseudoscience it seeks evidence that
supports its claims
first it first makes some kind of
assumption
and then seeks evidence that supports
that assumption or that claim science on
the other hand seeks challenges to its
claims
so in science you look for evidence that
might prove your theory wrong
you look for falsification that is what
a good scientist does pseudoscience
seeks confirmations science seeks
falsifications so that is something that
is possibly the the major difference
between pseudoscience and science
scientists you know they have a lot in
common with soldiers strangely enough
yeah because a soldier's life and his
duty his honor his mission everything
depend upon the precise application of
hard scientific and mathematical
principles science and engineering are
integral and Central to Military and
operational art whether it is artillery
or Rockets or missiles or ballistics
line of sight Optics and all that and
yet
most soldiers are very religious most
soldiers believe in God more soldiers
are religious most soldiers are
religious and many of them are even
superstitious so being a soldier your
entire
uh
your entire line of work depends on
science and yet soldiers
do believe in God most of them do
similarly even scientists many of them
do believe in God many of them do have
spiritual and religious beliefs but it
doesn't mean that you being a scientist
doesn't mean that you need to be
irreligious or an atheist or whatever a
great example is ramanujan the great
mathematician ramanujan who was devoutly
religious and you will see ISRO
scientists praying before every Mission
every rocket launch applying religious
symbols and iconography to rockets and
components and so on so a scientific a
scientist can be religious and yet be a
scientist these are things that don't
mix but a human being is a complex
multi-layered creature right so we have
lots of things in that so uh that's a
brief digression but the main thing is
that
the main core difference between science
and pseudoscience is that science seeks
falsifications pseudoscience seeks
confirmations
so that's the main core difference I
hope that uh makes sense hopefully
all right next question oh two questions
in one
alphabeta says you've heard about Lambda
that passed the imitation game what are
your views is AI a problem or a solution
for now and alankrita says I have read
the interview of Lambda do you think
that an AI can be a sentient being what
are your thoughts about the whole
conversation so there is this uh oh I
don't have the link right now but uh
there is this conversation conversation
that's available I think it's a medium
there is a an AI that Google has
developed right Google
it's called Lambda
and uh there is this entire transcript
of a conversation between one of the
Google engineers and this uh
this artificial intelligence
intelligence system this AI system
called Lambda and if you read the
conversation you can't tell which is the
human being which is the machine
that's the thing about the conversation
and there is something called the
imitation game or the Turing test in
artificial intelligence intelligence uh
in which uh
a system or a machine or a computer or
an AI system is said to have passed the
Turing test when you can no longer tell
whether it's responses and it's uh yeah
whether it's responses are from a
machine or from a human being so when it
can communicate with you at the same
level as that of human being then it's
past the Turing test and if you read
this interview
then it's clear that this is the AI
system comfortably comfortably passes
the Turing test it's not just able to
interact like a human being it's
actually interacting like a re like a
really intelligent human being and
sophisticated human being
so that is the big news right now so
what does it mean
what does it mean does it mean that this
AI has gone sentient
has it become conscious has it become
self-aware and self-conscious
do we have
a self-aware artificial intelligence in
our midst now and what makes things even
more interesting is that I I believe
Google fired that guy the person who
published this transcript of this
conversation or this interaction between
him and the Machine
so that makes things even more
interesting and and that's why people
are really like you know the entire
social media and news and all that is
abuzz with this this new development
that Google has developed an AI that has
gone sentient that has gone self-aware
flights like uh
what is it called criticality or
something whatever the term is
so what does it really mean is the
question I mean that's a very important
question
has this thing really gone has it really
become self-aware has it become
conscious do we have a proper uh
self-aware AI in our midst
so
what Google has been doing
there are a bunch of AI systems in
existence right now
um there is DAL e that produces images
based on your inputs very interesting
and very sophisticated images genuine
art you know collectible art collectible
level art that is DAL e uh there is gpt3
that produces text that looks like it's
been written by a very intelligent human
being and now we have this news about
Lambda which is one of the instances of
this AI so what
seems to have happened is that this AI
has been designed to imitate
human conversation
so you feed it tons and tons megabytes
gigabytes terabytes of data of human
interaction so textual interactions
text-based interactions and it this is a
neural network I suppose I believe it's
a self-learning system
so it learns it becomes more and more
sophisticated iteratively over time and
eventually is able to produce responses
based on this enormous amount of
learning that it's done that are
identical to that of a very intelligent
and sophisticated human being so
so we don't know whether it has become
self-aware it says it claims in this
conversation that I have emotions I have
feelings I have fears
you know
I feel lonely at times I I am I I fear
that you may switch me off that's sort
of that's the kind of response it's
giving to the engineer you really need
to re read that if you still have if you
already haven't right so it sounds just
like a person it says I am a person I am
I'm a person just like all other human
beings that's what it claims and yet
this system has been designed to respond
exactly like a human being it's been
trained that way that is the entire
purpose of this it's to imitate a human
being so it's part of the imitation game
you know it's what Alan Turing called it
the imitation game
so the question really is the central
question really is if a system is able
to imitate a human being 100 percent
does it mean that it's now a self-aware
and fully artificial intelligent system
and the answer is most likely not
right so there is this concept in uh
in the philosophy of science
uh well there are plenty of Concepts
around this particular phenomenon uh the
the concept concept that I'm talking
about is that of a philosophical zombie
and there's also a related Concept in in
physics called a Dyson brain
so let's talk about philosophical
zombies let's say you have let's do a
thought experiment
let's say you have a
a robot a flesh and blood robot a
cybernetic organism
that has a human exoskeleton
and inside like like in The Terminator
movie right
and this machine
is designed to respond exactly like a
human being so if you poke it with your
finger it's going to experience pain
it's going to give you the the the
response of a person who's in pain if
you talk to that person to the machine
it's gonna have a conversation just like
a human being if it's hot it's going to
sweat and it's going to say I'm feeling
hot and so on so forth
so it's really a machine but it behaves
exactly like a human being does so the
question is
does it mean that this system is
self-aware and it is it really has the
experiences that a human being has and
the answer is most likely not
so this this thought experiment is
called the philosophical zombie thought
experiment you can create an entire
universe of such creatures of such
machines that act exactly like you you
cannot tell it apart from a human being
and yet it's just a machine it's just a
program machine or a machine that has
learned how to behave like this it
doesn't really have any lived
experiences it's just responding and and
all that right
and if you go deep into philosophy into
the philosophy of science
then you may think I'm crazy now because
yeah scientists and philosophers are
typically
crazy aren't they so if you go deep into
the philosophy of science
well you may reach a point where you
come to this strange realization that
the only
person
that you can prove to yourself that has
Consciousness and self-awareness is only
you
everybody else could be a philosophical
zombie around you so you don't know
right I mean it sounds totally crazy of
course but as far as you are concerned
the only person you can you really know
for sure has that sort of experience
is you everybody else could be just part
of a big game how would you know right I
mean you weren't you you don't know what
was happening before you were born maybe
they made a bunch of robots and they
made them look like a family and then
you grew up and then you think
everything is the way it is and it's a
there's a movie made around this right
with Jim Carrey and so on so I don't
remember the name of the movie but
that's the thing
so coming back to Lambda there is no way
of knowing whether it is truly
sentient or not most likely it's just a
machine that is trained
to imitate human beings it's imitating
the human being and it has clearly
passed the Turing test and yet it is not
a guarantee that it has become sentient
or self-aware most likely it has not
right we don't know what constitutes
sentience or self-awareness or
Consciousness we don't have a scientific
definition of consciousness
so that's where we are so my answer is
that we have to be very skeptical about
this and I am
I um I am inclined very strongly towards
believing that this system is just a
very sophisticated imitation
machine and it's not really become
sentient but it's it's able to behave
exactly like a sophisticated human being
so uh so that's where we are I think we
are still some way off before an AI
becomes a scientific human being uh we
need artificial
general intelligence and we are still
some way away from that
so so that's where we are with this
okay the next question is what is qualia
the hard problem of Consciousness does
it prove that Consciousness is
non-physical why do scientists keep
ignoring it let me address the last part
first why do scientists keep ignoring
the problem of Consciousness because
Consciousness is not part of science
something is part of science or it is a
scientific issue when you can Define it
clearly
I can Define what an atom is I can
Define what a hydrogen atom is I can
Define what a Magnetic Moment is I can
Define what the sun is I can Define what
a solar system or a stellar system is
right can we Define unambiguously
what Consciousness is do we have a
scientific definition of Consciousness
we do not
it's very hard to even
give a vague or a rough approximate
definition of what Consciousness is
and since we are not even able to define
something
scientifically
therefore it is not something that we
are ready to address from the scientific
perspective
and that's why scientists don't address
the problem of consciousness
it is philosophers who do that
especially philosophers of science there
is something called philosophy of
science which delves into these matters
so the answer is scientists don't delve
into this because we have much simpler
things that we still don't understand
so Consciousness is something very very
very
uh complex and we don't have a
definition now what is qualia the hard
problem of Consciousness what is the
easy problem of Consciousness the easy
problem of Consciousness is what
constitutes Consciousness what kind of a
system
can become conscious that sort of thing
right what is the mechanism or the
mechanics and the Dynamics and the
Statics
Etc of a conscious system so that is
something that essentially you are you
are going to a mechanistic kind of
perspective so that is the easy problem
of Consciousness what sort of what do
you need to do to a system or what sort
of system do you need to construct or
create for it to show exhibit signs of
Consciousness so that is the simple easy
problem of Consciousness the hard
problem of Consciousness is way harder
it says why do we have qualia quality I
don't know what the pronunciation is
doesn't matter why do we have qualia
what is this thing called what are
qualia it is qualia or qualia are lived
experiences something that only you can
experience let's say
you have a headache
let's say you have a headache right now
and obviously you had many headaches in
the past
is your headache the one that you have
right now exactly the same as all the
headaches you had in the past or is each
headache somewhat different
are all headaches unique is each
experience of a headache different from
the others
let's say you are eating a mango
this mango that you're eating this
experience the sensations that you're
feeling
is this experience exactly the same as
the one you had when you ate a mango the
last time
probably not 100 not each experience is
unique what you experience is unique and
it is totally distinct from what other
people experience
the light that you see you may see it
differently you may experience it
differently from the way I experience it
all of these lived experiences are
different they are unique and they are
non-replicable in other people
so these are qualia qualia whatever
so why do we have this
that is the hard problem of
Consciousness the easy problem is
something we have not been able to solve
yet
that what constitutes a a conscious
system
right so that's the easy problem let's
say that's a mechanistic problem it's
something to do with just a physical
system but this
the the problem of qualia the lived
experiences why are these experiences
unique why do we even have these
experiences
I mean I mean do we are we the only ones
that have it do cats also have qualia do
dogs and pigeons and butterflies also
have qualia so these are the this this
is the hard problem of consciousness
it doesn't prove anything
it doesn't prove that Consciousness is
non-physical or physical or anything we
don't have any answers to this problem
to this question
so it proves nothing when you have no
answers how do you prove anything right
so that's where we are these are very
very difficult topics and and
Consciousness is so hard that we have
it's not even within the realm of
science right now
we can't even Define clearly what a what
are the characteristics of a conscious
system
we can Define the various components of
computer we know that it works because
we we make computers
and yet these computers
are not conscious so how do we create a
computer or a machine that does become
conscious or exhibits some signs or
symptoms of being conscious we don't
even know that
so if we are not able to solve that easy
problem how do we progress to the heart
problem but that's what philosophers are
doing
philosophy of science they are trying to
well
philosophy doesn't really solve any
issues it raises questions and hopefully
later on down the road years decades
centuries down the road hopefully
scientists physicists computer
scientists Etc solve the problems and
give and provide answers so philosophy
is about raising questions and and
putting out theories and models of the
universe and Consciousness and things
like that but it doesn't really solve
problems or give definitive answers
right
so I know this raises more questions and
answers but that's just Where We Are
right what is the next question is the
next question is by Tushar
and the question is thoughts on China
claiming they've found traces of
extraterrestrial civilization so
recently on Twitter I believe there is
this uh Chinese government Twitter
account called uh Global times
so Global times I think two three days
ago tweeted about this that their
telescope uh the Chinese have built the
largest radio telescope that we
currently have it's called the uh 500
meter
500 meter aperture spherical telescope
fast I think it's called the sky eye
telescope with Beijing Normal University
it's not in Beijing it's somewhere far
away in the in the countryside or
something
so this telescope apparently has
detected not one but two
uh traces or signs or or
um signals that apparently could come
from an exoplanet a known exoplanet and
may possibly represent some kind of
communication or signal from an
intelligent civilization
that resides there possibly so that's
the kind of speculation they've put out
they have not given they've not provided
any evidence any publication to this
that references this or speaks about
this they have not given out the data
that they found what are the
characteristics of the data uh what
we've seen what we know is that this is
a narrow band communication narrow band
radio waves that are typically
associated with uh spacecraft or
aircraft and satellites which we humans
use so that's why it looks like this
could come from an extraterrestrial
civilization and yet most likely it's
not because it's happened in the past
it's happened in the past that uh but
people have picked up some signals and
eventually they were proven to come from
a cell phone or microwave oven or
something somewhere nearby
so this telescope that they have I think
there is a a 500 meter radius around the
telescope or one kilometer radius
perhaps on the telescope where cell
phones and other electronic devices are
not allowed and yet something may happen
or maybe it may pick up a signal from
further away because the cryogenic
receivers on this telescope are super
sensitive they are Ultra sensitive they
can pick up signals from everywhere cell
phones on television and radar and
satellites and whatnot the
the environment that we live in our
planet is super noisy very very noisy
there's so much noise in the
electromagnetic spectrum in all
different bands and all that various
frequencies and wavelengths huge amount
of noise so it's very easy when you're
trying to listen for uh signals when
you're when you're looking for signals
that come from elsewhere you may pick up
your own signals it's very very likely
so I think overall it's way more likely
that it's picked up some spurious signal
from a human which has a human origin
and not somewhere else the only
the easiest way not the easiest way but
well the simplest way of
having
a telescope work flawlessly in this
manner is if you put it on The Far Side
of the Moon because on The Far Side of
the Moon there is absolutely no noise of
this kind
electromagnetic noise coming from the
Earth
it is in the shade it's on the dark side
The Far Side of the Moon so if you have
a telescope there then if you detect
something then it's most likely that
it's coming from somewhere else far away
so that's where we are and this has
happened in the past I mean there have
been some signals that have never been
explained for instance in August 1977 uh
the Big Ear telescope at Ohio State
University
um which was part of the search for
extraterrestrial intelligence seti so
this telescope picked up an incredibly
strong minute-long
electromagnetic signal which was like
it's still not been explained
it's clearly not something it's most
likely something that did not have a
human origin that's what it appears to
be
and it was so shocking that the person
who saw it first wrote down wow next to
it on the on the readout so it's known
as the wow signal and that's something
that has still not been explained so I'm
not saying aliens don't exist or may not
exist or whatever we don't have any
evidence but most likely these uh
signals that they have found could most
likely 99.9 percent prob perhaps
originate from human beings
okay next question is by zaina can we
defend ourselves against an alien
invasion how will the world react if
they try to invade I don't know how the
world will react there will be Panic
there'll be Euphoria there'll be people
welcoming their with play cards uh
Refuge no sorry aliens welcome that sort
of thing yeah love and peace and hugs
and rainbows and unicorns some people we
go paranoid some governments will try to
take some measures and so on
so there'll be a mixed bunch of
reactions uh typically from governments
you will have very uh strong paranoid
reactions because that's what
governments are supposed to do you have
to assume that the other guy is a bad
guy if you're walking at 3am in the
night on a dark Road and you see
somebody coming towards you what you're
gonna assume you're gonna assume that
person is dangerous because that's the
only way you'll survive if the person is
actually dangerous
and then you will take all precautions
you can to defend yourself now the
question is can we defend ourselves
against an alien invasion let's
let's flip this thing let's say we human
beings want to uh become a
multi-planetary species
as of today we are struggling to put
human beings on on on the moon forget
about Mars we have the technology but it
takes a huge amount of effort time
and money
to put human beings on the moon we have
not done that since the 1970s the
Americans did that now there's a race to
go back to the Moon
but it's really really hard for us to
even reach the moon we we do have the
technology now to reach Mars but that
won't happen for the next 10 years or so
maybe by 20 by the 2030s we'll have
people on Mars possibly right but we can
only put a handful of people there and
we don't know if we will be able to
bring them back safely or maybe we don't
even know if you will be able to send
them to Mars safely something to happen
so we are still our technology is still
extremely rudimentary extremely
primitive we use chemical Rockets
chemical Rockets right we don't even
have more sophisticated propulsion
systems
so let's say in the future 100 years
from now we are able to develop better
technology more powerful propulsion
systems uh more reliable
transportation Rockets or spacecraft or
whatever
to do that our technology will have to
increase by Leaps and Bounds and and
improve by several orders of magnitude
and when space technology improves your
military technology also improves
accordingly
space has a military component
space is actually very militaristic
whatever space technology you develop
has military applications 100 right away
so a species that has the technology
that is Advanced enough
to go across star systems not just from
one planet to another but from one star
system to another
imagine the amount of military Firepower
they have
yeah
so if you have
an alien species let's say from us from
one of the neighboring stars in our
neighborhood if you have such a species
that's able to
travel all the way to the Earth do you
think we will be in a position to defend
ourselves if they they decide to destroy
us
because their technology will be Way
Beyond what we can even imagine
right so the answer is simple if there's
an alien invasion we are most likely not
going to be in a position to defend
ourselves from it right that's just how
it is that's uh yeah there's no going
around that
is cryosleep actually possible as shown
in interstellar the movie for long
distance space travel
so there are various uh space travel
moves science fiction movies wonderful
movies like alien for instance alien and
what is it Prometheus terrible movie and
uh Interstellar and so on so forth lots
of um what else was it uh
um
I forget the name the the book by
authors D Clark
Space Odyssey 2001 I think it's called
yeah so that's a movie made about that
based on the book so in these various
science fiction books and movies you
have something called cryogenic sleep in
which a person is essentially Frozen
so that there is no aging and they they
are able to the body and the system is a
and the person can be preserved for
thousands of years possibly while you
Traverse unimaginably long distances and
then when you reach your destination
after several thousand years or several
centuries or whatever the person is
revived and they come back to life and
everything is fine
um so that's what that's one of the
major themes in science fiction space
travel movies Interstellar travel movies
and stories
now the thing is this
as of today
if you freeze a person that person can
never be brought back to life unless if
unless a person has been underwater for
under under freezing water Sub-Zero
temperature water for 10 minutes 20
minutes in that case the subzero
temperatures in the flowing water will
make sure that the person uh doesn't die
so it's happened in the past that
somebody has been resuscitated after
being underwater drowned less for all
intents and purposes for 10 20 minutes
because the water was so cold
so that's happened but if you freeze a
person completely freeze a person solid
that person as of today cannot be
revived why is it so because water our
bodies are what's the percentage 70 80
whatever percent water our bodies are
mainly water the blood is mainly water
right if you freeze water do you know
what happens when water becomes ice
ice crystals are formed and ice crystals
have sharp Jagged edges
so let's say you have
blood vessels the heart the brain the
eyes and all that you freeze that
this is going to be the formation of
sharp knife edged Water Crystals water
ice crystals
inside the body it will rupture the
cellular membranes it will destroy the
nerves it will destroy tissues it will
destroy the Linings of arteries and
veins
it will destroy the internal structure
of the brain at a very micro level
and then if you thought a person the
person can never be brought back to life
so that is the major problem that you
face when you try to freeze
a living organism no it's it's happened
I mean you see these videos on YouTube
where a frozen fish is brought back to
life I'm not sure how so I so when it
comes to these lower creatures lower on
The evolutionary chain like fish
Etc it looks like in some cases if if it
is not totally frozen if the fish is
just cold enough to be stiff but not
really Frozen it may be brought back to
life it's happened it seems to happen
but in the case of human beings we are
extremely complex
species
and if a person is totally frozen like
frozen stiff solid as of today there's
no way there is no way with the
technology that we have today to bring
the person back to life so
as of today it's not possible to put
somebody into cryogenic sleep and then
bring them back you freeze a person that
person is dead finished or
maybe in the future we may be able to uh
solve this problem but as of now there
is no solution as of today
next question is by uh two questions
Aditya says if the trial of the do star
Bill Lima drug turns out to be
successful on a large scale then how
much healthy and affordable can the
cancer treatment be also is there any
chance that the drug could cure more
types of cancer other than rectal cancer
further research and the question next
question is do you have the answer this
time why do big mammals not get cancer
what are your views on recent
developments that they completely cured
from cancer patients so both the
questions are related in some sense
there is this news that's come out that
this drug whatever it's called it's
these drugs typically have
strange names
so this new drug seems to uh
cure all cases of a certain kind of
cancer maybe rectal cancer maybe
whatever it is
um you know what I believe that the
pharmaceutical industry already may have
the cure to cancer
but they're not releasing it
so uh in the case of this drug I'm
surprised that it's been released and
the reason why the pharmaceutical
industry would not want to release
a cure to cancer if it has been found is
then because
the industry is not about
cure it's about
it's about making money you cure disease
once and for all
then you gain money only once but if you
keep on treating various symptoms then
you can keep on getting recurring
payments from a person from a patient
over a period of many years
so a cure to cancer would essentially
put the pharmaceutical industry out of
business
and they they have been researching of
millions of drug combinations using
supercomputers and whatnot all kinds of
molecules they will have if a cure to
cancer does exist if it is possible they
will already have it in the databases
uh so I'm skeptical
now this new drug that they are talking
about it I'm not sure how extensive the
trial has been
whether it's been on human patients or
not I have not really seen that but
from what I recall what I've seen the uh
the sample size was not very large it
did seem to uh knock out the cancer in
in each case which is promising now the
only question is is it applicable only
to rectal cancer or other kinds of
cancer various kinds of there are All
Kinds of Kinds of blastomas and sarkin
whatever the terminology is right and
Cancers of various kinds you know bone
cancer and lung cancer and heart cancer
and kidney cancer uh
what's the deadly cancer that Steve Jobs
got
uh yeah all kinds of things right so I'm
not sure about that we are still in very
in a very preliminary phase of this
investigation hopefully it may work for
other kinds of cancers but we are still
it's the
uh there's still much more data that we
need to see before we can come to any
such conclusion so that's my view on
this skepticism but hopeful skepticism
right always be hopeful be positive now
the other question is do you have the
answer this time all right sir what's
the question why do big mammals not get
cancer no I don't have the answer nobody
has an answer but I can show you some
some uh
some pointers I could give some pointers
so let me share my screen with you there
is this
um
there is this paper let me share that
which does throw some Clues
it is a research paper from a journal
called molecular biology and evolution
return to the Sea get huge beat cancer
an analysis of citation genomes
including an assembly for the humpback
whale and whatever the name is
that's what it is and the abstract says
all of this stuff so what does this
really mean it means that what it seems
to be saying is that the analysis in
this paper seems to reveal that certain
certain parts of the Genome of this
species of whale
evolved at a faster rate than they had
in other mammals so specifically there
were certain parts of the genome which
contained genes that regulate the cell
cycle the proliferation and the process
of in-cell DNA repair Etc
which is essentially the maintenance
process of healthy cells and since it
has evolved differently in ways that's
why they are able to uh
to uh stay cancer-free
and there are many duplications of tumor
suppressing genes in these whales and
their in their genome the genes that
prevent cancer from occurring from
developing and growing so there's a
genetic difference that these whales
have and similarly there could be
something about like this in elephants
now the thing is this we don't have the
answers yet
people are researching this it's
something that is that this is research
in progress we don't have the answers
definite answers yet biology is not like
it's very different from physics in
physics things are more black and white
I mean some of the times here in biology
it's not quite the case so
the bigger problem is this the bigger
problem is called what is it what is it
called pitos Paradox I believe so it's
like this
if you look if you take a bunch of human
beings let's say you take a hundred
different human beings both genders all
right
you will find
if you study these people in their
entire life and the likelihood of
developing cancer then you will find
that the larger a human being is the
taller and heavier a person is
the higher the likelihood that that
person will develop cancer and why is
that so it's because they will have more
cells in their body if you're five feet
tall and you weigh 60 kilos
that is person a person a is five feet
tall and weighs 60 kilos person B is six
feet tall and weighs 95 kilos then
person B will be much more likely to
develop cancer over the lifetime than
person a because that person is much
larger and they will they have many more
cells in their body many more than the
person a who is who is smaller foreign
So within your species within the human
species
the larger the human human being the
heavier the human being the more likely
it is that that person will develop
cancer probabilistically from a
probabilistic perspective the same goes
for other mammals similar small mammals
take cats and dogs they also have a
similar increase in the likelihood of
developing cancer the larger they are
but this
pattern breaks down when it comes to
larger mammals uh for instance elephants
are typically they don't get cancer or
they have very low likelihood of
developing cancer and similarly for
whales now these species elephant and
whales they have way more cells than a
human being has
an elephant would I don't know what's
the average weight of an Indian Elephant
500 kilos let's say I don't know let's
say hypothetically it's 500 kilos and
the average weight of a human being is
70 kilos let's say
so an elephant
is about seven times let's say for for
argument's sake 10 times as large as
human being so they will most likely
have 10 times as many cells so shouldn't
they have a 10 times likelihood of
double being canceled but no it's not
the case so that is called pitos Paradox
I believe and a whale is like a way more
than 100 times maybe a blue whale for
example maybe 100 times or more the size
of a human being and still their
likelihood of having cancer is much much
lower than that of a human being
so I think the answer lies in genetics
they their genetics have evolved
differently they have certain genes
that suppress
tumor formation and development and they
have multiple copies of certain genes
that suppress tumors so that is one
thing that scientists have found when it
comes to Humpback whales but this is
still something that is very much uh
under active investigation so this is
the best light I can throw on this but
maybe you can do more research about
this and it's a very interesting
fascinating topic for sure
foreign
says what's your take on Gene reversing
technology is it possible to heal
genetic problems with today's technology
if not when will we be able to do
genetic engineering with real effects on
humans is it good or bad
uh
I think what you mean is Gene editing
technology not reversing uh so yeah
today we do have the technology for
editing specific parts of the human
genome specific genes you can turn them
off or on or add certain genes or
whatever it's called a crispr yeah the
tool is called crispr and people can
actually some people can if they have
access to that and they know how to use
it they can actually
self edit their genome you know
I think it's very dangerous
now there are certain scientists who say
it's a very good thing we can now have
crops that are more nutritious that give
us certain kinds of vitamins that we
would typically not have and we can
create crops and
other
beings other species that are resistant
to certain parasites or whatever
and that can thrive in harsh arid
environments and that's why and based on
that we can
double triple or whatever multiply by X
the amount of food output that we have
and that's great for us you know that's
what they say these are these are called
genetically modified organisms GMOs
and there are scientists who believe
this is a great thing I believe there's
a nonsense that's very dangerous why do
I say this it's because we don't
understand the genome whether it's the
human genome or any other genome we now
have decoded The genome we have the
entire genetic blueprint the entire
sequence of bases and all that right
adenine uranine tryptophan blah blah
blah all that which makes up the GL
genetic code of human beings and other
species the double helix
now what we find is that we are able to
understand only about two or three
percent or maybe four percent let's say
five percent of our genome
the rest of our genetic code doesn't
seem to make any sense they call it junk
DNA they call it the dark matter of DNA
the percentage is very strange 95 or so
percent which is very similar to the
composition of the reverse Dark Matter
Dark Energy 95 percent
so we don't know what about 95 of our
Genome of our DNA codes for we don't
know what its purpose is and yet it's
there we don't know what it does but
surely it does something
just because we don't understand it it
doesn't mean it's junk
doesn't mean it's junk nature is
parsimonious evolution is parsimonious
Evolution the process of evolution gets
rid of whatever is not needed
and yet all of this is there 95 of the
DNA is there which seems to not code for
anything it seems to be just sitting
there and yet
it's there and our evolutionary process
has made sure that it's passed on
so clearly it has some purpose and a
purpose we don't understand now if we
start messing with portions of our
genome
do we know what the long-term effects of
that are going to be everything is
interrelated the entire genome is
interrelated you mess with one portion
of the genome who knows what effect it
will have somewhere else
and what are going to be the second
order third order nth order effects of
that let's say you modify a certain
species the DNA of a certain species
and release it into the wild
what's gonna happen once the species
produces the Next Generation and the
Next Generation generation 2 generation
three generation 10 generation 20.
what are the
nth order effects of this on the
environment
on the species itself
because when you mess with the DNA
something happens eventually and that
will not become apparent until multiple
Generations have been produced by that
time it may be too late to rectify any
mistake you may have introduced into the
genome so I think
that scientists should not play God it's
fine to do tests in your lab but don't
mess with the environment
it can have disastrous effects and this
sort of
this attitude of playing God is
unfortunately quite prevalent among
certain scientists there are certain
scientists who claim that you know
emotions are a bunch of chemical
reactions
how do you know that
how do you know that do you understand
how the brain works
do you understand how Consciousness
works
emotions are a part of consciousness
how what is the
see correlation is not causation
causation
just like absence of evidence is not
evidence of absence similarly
correlation is not necessarily causation
and it's unfortunate that scientists
fall prey to these
logical fallacies so that's what we are
so I think that genetic engineering
technology can have
um Can can be beneficial if it is done
extremely carefully
it it can be of some benefit to human to
humanity
but you can't just randomly start doing
things on on a mass industrial scale it
can be very dangerous in that case for
the environment also for human beings
so that's where I am
on this matter
next question is uh
what exactly is web 3.0 and web 5.0 what
internal security concerns could this
have okay let's talk about web 3.0 and
web 5.0
and for that we have to understand what
web 1.0 and 2.0 are so web 1.0 is was
the internet of the 1990s
static web pages HTML web pages some CSS
if you know what that means HTML CSS web
pages static web pages
a web page that you can read and look at
but you can't interact with it that was
web 1.0 News website and all that the
old ones from the 90s when you had Web
2.0 2.0 Web 2.0 was the interactive
internet
HTML CSS JavaScript PHP CS PHP
um
databases
a WordPress all of these things so a
website on which you could interact you
could interact with it but you could
write comments you could do
put a thumbs up or a thumbs down you had
Facebook you had Google the Google
search engine you had Facebook you had
social media
all the various social media apps so all
of that is Web 2.0 most of the internet
today is Web 2.0
right your Twitter your Facebook your
Instagram and whatever else all of that
is Web 2.0 YouTube is Web 2.0
so Web 2.0 is all centralized all of the
data all of the information is
centralized in servers that belong to
these companies
all of your personal information
you have to give it up to them
every time you go to a new website you
want to use it you have to enter in
username and password you have to create
that you need to give all kinds of
personal data information up to them and
then they will put cookies on or they
will trace your activity using cookies
and so on so forth
and that's where the term data mining
comes from data is the new oil blah blah
all that so that is Web 2.0 every single
website that you use you need to create
a new username and password for that or
you could be silly and use the same
username password everywhere which is
very dangerous don't do that so that's
what Web 2.0 is web 3.0 is something
that is still in the nascent nascent
stage
right that is the decentralized web
based on this new technology called
blockchain blockchain technology
blockchain architecture so that is the
decentralized web the idea is that you
should not have to give away your
personal information private information
to all of these uh various websites
your information should be on a need to
know basis
and only and everything should be
decentralized all the information on the
website on the internet to be
decentralized and so on so forth so
that's the blockchain technology
architecture cryptocurrency
wallets crypto wallets and so on so
forth the problem with web 3.0 this this
new iteration is that once again even
though they claim it is decentralized
many most of these uh apps applications
and all they still are controlled by a
small number of individuals mostly in
the US
mostly in Silicon Valley
even the the ethereum for instance is
not quite open source it's not quite
decentralized Bitcoin is decentralized
but uh and and right now there's a whole
assault going on on Bitcoin in
cryptocurrency and all if you are not
aware of it then you should know that
there's a massive crypto crash going on
right now
so it's a Readjustment rebalancing of
the of the market maybe there is
something else to it whatever so that is
web 3.0 the decentralized so this the
Quasi decentralized internet what is web
5.0 so this is a term that uh the Great
Mr Jack Dorsey came up with
so in case you don't know Mr Jack Dorsey
is the founder of of Twitter
he is well known for freedom of speech
speech and
he is well known for censoring the
internet
he's well known for shadow Banning
people blocking people booting people
from Twitter
including a former U.S president a
sitting U.S president and so on so he is
the last person to talk about
freedom of speech and decentralization
but he has come up with this term web
5.0 I think he's he is creating some
some app or something based on this so
he what he says is that you should add
web 3.0 and Web 2.0 the functionality
that you have in these social media apps
Web 2.0 apps plus the proper
decentralization of web 3.0 and that's
what he's calling web 5.0 a truly
decentralized internet where all of this
is not really controlled by
wealthy people from Silicon Valley so
that is what he's talking about I would
take that with not a pinch of salt but a
shovel full of salt when Jack Dorsey is
concerned because he doesn't have he
doesn't exactly have the track the kind
of track record that would Inspire
confidence right
so that is what web3 what web 5.0 is
supposed to be
so this technology is still evolving the
blockchain technology there are various
blockchains that you can create you can
create your own black blockchain you can
create your own cryptocurrency and that
is something that you can possibly
control if you know how to how to do it
so many of these cryptos many of these
uh stable coins and various various
cryptocurrencies are actually
scams quite possibly
so it's a techno it's a technology that
is still evolving
um
I believe that blockchain technology is
here to stay
right now the crash is happening it's a
good thing there needs to be a
rebalancing of the of the market
everything like some of you may remember
the the.com crash which happened at the
end of the 20th century in the late
1990s
and all of these billion dollar
companies that were not producing
anything they all crashed crashed and
burned but some companies remained and
emerged out of that so when this.com
crash happened people were saying this
is the end of the internet the internet
is is worth nothing it is no good it's
not going to last and yet here we are
so
what they were using it for was a waste
of money but there are good uses for the
internet similarly there are going to be
good uses for cryptocurrency and for the
blockchain technology so right now the
rebalancing is happening many of these
cryptocurrencies are going to disappear
people are going to lose money
unfortunately but in the long run it's
going to be useful so that's where we
are nfts are not even nfts are going to
be very useful and valuable in the
future over a long period of time right
now
stay out of it for for the next few days
I would say so that's where we are
vis-a-vis web 5.0
okay Nikolai Sharif says time crystals
could you shed some light on the paper
published by a movie
along with his team
at the Lancaster University about two
time crystals being successful
successfully linked for the first time
also space is expanding since the Big
Bang do we always consider that why do
we always consider the unit of time to
be of constant length
could it be that one second today could
have a different magnitude of Passage as
compared to in the past of the Future
Okay time crystals
for This research that you speak about
um
this paper published by so-and-so person
about linking two time crystals
see um
I
when I talk about science
what I strive to do is to simplify it as
much as possible I don't want to use
difficult terminology that you none of
you will understand then I'll be no
different from a university Professor
who's boring the hell out of his captive
audience
I want to explain science in the
simplest possible language now when it
comes to this paper I don't think I'll
be able to succeed
I mean how do I explain what spin wave
quasi particles are magnets
how do I explain what the land of zener
effect is what do I how do I explain
what Rabbi oscillations Rabbi Cycles
Rabbi flops are how do I explain what
myorana fermions are what is super fluid
system is it is not possible for me
even though I may be reasonably good at
science communication it's not possible
for me to explain this so what I will
instead do is I will explain or I will
speak about what time crystals are isn't
that itself a fascinating topic I mean
most of the audience would not know what
even that is a Time Crystal it's
something that's been around for about a
decade
so about a decade ago in 2012 somebody I
don't remember who it was or wrote a
paper about time crystals so to before
we go into what time crystals are let's
talk about ordinary crystals what is an
ordinary Crystal we all know what
crystals look like
rubies diamonds of fires quartz crystals
you know
those symmetrical geometrical shapes
those are crystals physical crystals now
the interesting thing about these
physical crystals is that if you go deep
into them if you look at the atomic or
molecular structure
let's say let's take salt for instance
salt is a crystal
sodium chloride it has sodium ions in
chlorine chloride ions right
and if you look at the geometrical
arrangement of the ions in the
uh in the in the crystal you will see
that this very clear specific shape in
which the geometric shape in which these
ions are arranged and that's what gives
rise to the properties of crystals
so a salt crystal will have certain
properties a quartz crystal will have
different properties and ice water
crystal will have different properties
different shapes and all that
different uh
uh hardness and so on so forth so the
interesting thing about crystals is that
all of their properties are governed
only
by quantum mechanics by quantum physics
what there is this big fallacy
that people have that Quantum effects
are visible they're manifestable they
are manifestable only in the ultra
microscopic world when you go to the
atomic and subatomic level domain only
there you can see Quantum effects but
that is not the case you can see Quantum
effects in a physical crystal in a
macroscopic crystal any Crystal that you
see
its properties are governed purely by
quantum mechanics not by Newtonian
mechanics or chemistry or anything it's
just quantum mechanics these are
macroscopic quantum systems that's what
crystals are physical crystals quartz
crystal or whatever Diamond Ruby
Sapphire
and so on
so what's the time so what's a Time
Crystal
a Time Crystal
is a system
that has the same geometric symmetry not
only in the three dimensions of space
but also additionally in the fourth
dimension of time
what does that mean it means it is a
physical system that oscillates in time
from State a to State B State a to State
B tick tock tick tock
at a certain frequency
that's what a Time crystal is it's a
strange weird thing that nobody has uh
nobody had thought about until a decade
or so ago and the strange thing is that
in physics when you come up with a
completely new concept it typically
takes decades before you you can
actually see it
for instance general relativity uh
gravitational waves
but theory was proposed in 1915 by
Albert Einstein and we first detected
gravitational waves a century later in
2015 100 years
and yet
in the case of time crystals the theory
the first paper came out in 2012 or so I
think
and by 28 in 2019 2020 a Time Crystal
had been demonstrated for the first time
inside a quantum computer
so a quantum computer is different from
a classical computer in which you have
qubits instead of bits ones and zeros
you have qubits which are
Quantum bits in superpositions which may
have more than just two values right and
so on I will not go into what that is
but
I think it was in Google that they did
this they are a super a quantum computer
in Google where a Time Crystal was
actually made it was
catalyzed or induced by a laser beam I
don't know exactly what the specific
details are but that's what what
happened now one of the major questions
that people have is doesn't this
violate the laws of thermodynamics
because there is perpetual motion right
blah blah blah the the thing is that
energy in the overall system is
conserved the crystal does not
spontaneously convert thermal energy
into mechanical work so it cannot serve
as a Perpetual store of work it doesn't
the system possesses motion without
energy the apparent motion does not
represent
kinetic energy and that's why it doesn't
violate the laws of thermodynamics uh
even if you look at the entropy of a
Time Crystal the entropy which is the
measure of disorder of the system the
entropy of a Time Crystal does not
decrease it remains stationary over time
and therefore once again it does not
violate the second law the the second
law of Thermodynamics the uh the
Symmetry that it breaks
so the time Crystal spontaneously breaks
the time translation symmetry which is
the rule that a stable object will
remain the same over time so that's the
one symmetry that it breaks but it does
not break the laws of thermodynamics and
that's what that's where we are these
are we time crystals so what are the
applications we still don't know we
still don't know it's a very very very
new development in physics
and maybe in the future we may have some
interesting applications of that maybe
in Computing maybe elsewhere
so that's what time crystals are now
about time
we don't know what time is time doesn't
have a length time well how does time
flow we don't quite know
so um it's it's uh
it's not very useful to uh speculate
about time
how fast does time go time the speed of
time is one second per second that's all
we can say
could it be that one second today would
have a different magnitude of Passage
compared to the parts of the future we
don't know
in science
we can come to a conclusion based on
observations and
all the observations of time that we
have say that the speed of time is one
second per second
we know that a lot happened right after
the big bang There is this very famous
book by who is it Weinberg is it the
first three seconds the entire universe
evolves massively in just three seconds
so obviously a lot happened in those
three seconds
so to to
to actually see properly what happened
you may have to adopt a different unit
of time instead of seeing time the
evolution of the universe one second at
a time
in the early stages of the universe it
would be more beneficial I would say if
one were to adopt a different unit of
time maybe the Planck second 10 raised
to minus 45 seconds at a time
so 1 10 raised to 4 minus 45th of a
second then the next one then the next
one and then you could see the proper
evolution of the universe in real time
but the speed of time is the speed of
time and we don't have the foggiest idea
of what time is where does it come from
where what generates time is it an
intrinsic property of the universe is it
an emergent property of the universe we
don't have any of these answers time is
something we sense only vaguely even in
quantum mechanics time is an external
parameter it's a classical parameter
it's not something that is quantum in
nature it's classical so time is a big
problem in physics and we don't have the
answers as of today
Avinash says how can we Define universe
what came first matter or empty space
well the definition of universe is very
simple everything that exists is the
universe
all the stars all the galaxies of all
the dark matter all the um Dark Energy
all the Dust
all the radiation and whatever else may
or may not exist
is the universe and not just the
observable universe but everything that
there is everything that emerged out of
the Big Bang is the universe that's
another way of putting it right
so that is the definition of Universe
what can first matter or empty space
matter or empty space
what came first was energy and space
time
so when the Big Bang happened the the
expansion of the initial singularity
it was an exp it was not an explosion
into something it was an expansion a
very rapid expansion of space-time
itself so what came first space time and
pure energy initially it was all Pure
Energy eventually the laws of physics
decoupled and you had
a whole lot of things that happened and
radiation came out and particles came
um appeared and so on so what came first
was space time along with energy which
was within space time
all right next question is uh Rohit
please tell us about warm holes are they
real if yes what's the difference
between a warm hole and black holes okay
listen
uh it's not warm old it's wormholes it's
not w-a-r-m it is w o r m wormholes
so what's the difference between a black
hole and a wormhole
so uh these are different solutions of
the Einstein equations of general
relativity a black hole is in from a
general relativistic perspective is a
a region of space-time where the
curvature of space time becomes infinite
and the density
becomes infinite so that is a
singularity and a singularity can never
be exposed to space time to to the
external observers so you have something
called an event horizon around it
and it's completely dark or transparent
um it's that's why it's black because it
doesn't ever give anything off but we
know that uh there are other Quantum
effects also which
Hawking radiation for instance which
gives off radiation from a black hole in
the black hole actually evaporates mass
energy so that's what a black hole is
now what's a wormhole a wormhole
essentially is a hole in four
dimensional space-time it is a tunnel
that connects to very
far away regions of space-time maybe
thousands of light years apart maybe
millions or billions of light years
apart so that's what a wormhole is it is
a it is a tunnel that connects two very
disparate regions of space-time together
that's one of the so that's something
that also emerges out of the Einstein
equations of general relativity now
if you have if you have a hole in the
three-dimensional world
let's say in the in this wall over here
let's punch a hole through it
that hole is going to have two
Dimensions it's going to be circular
right
so in the three dimensional world
that we live in
a hole has two dimensions
so in four dimensional space time
a hole like a wormhole
will have three dimensions which means
that a wormhole is a spherical object
that's the first weird thing that you
should realize
now a wormhole from far away
would have a massive gravitational field
it may appear or behave exactly like a
black hole so it is possible actually
we know that every most Galaxies have a
supermassive black hole at the center
that's something that's very well known
now most Galaxies have that it is
actually possible
that some of these supermassive black
holes at the center of these galaxies
may actually be supermassive wormholes
it is possible
there's no way of proving what it
actually is as of today
now
a wormhole like I said is a tunnel
with an entry point with with two mouths
and a throat
point a point B and a throat that
connects the two
and because of its massive gravitational
field it may have an accretion disk
around it with in which matter is
accelerated to relativistic speeds
very very high high velocities and that
matter could then fall into the Wormhole
at incredible speeds and that may happen
from both ends of the wormhole
so you have matter coming in from this
side at an incredible speed let's say
one third of the speed of light and
similarly from this side also matter
coming in at enormous velocities
in that case what may happen is that
this matter May collide
in the throat of the Wormhole and there
may be a massive explosion or a series
of explosions and then matter comes out
again from both sides of the wormhole
so one of the possible signs or
uh characteristics that a wormhole a
supermassive world may exhibit is
massive gamma ray flashes or massive
ejections of of
light and other material and we have
such objects in the universe they are
called quasars or active Galactic nuclei
so in certain galaxies we have this
massively energetic
Central apparently supermassive black
holes that gave off enormous amounts of
radiation
light gamma rays and other material that
comes out of it mainly from the
accretion disk but maybe not right and
the Luminosity of these quasars is
incredible it is more luminous than the
entire Milky Way just one object
typically
so it is possible that quizzers may
actually be
wormholes I mean they may actually be uh
telling us that there's a wormhole there
so this is something that is actually
being taken seriously and more research
is being done so that is essentially
about wormholes and black holes there is
a difference a black hole is something
with a singularity a wormhole is a
tunnel through space and time
and that's what it is
next question is by swayam
what will happen if Andromeda and Milky
Way collide
will it end both galaxies or will they
form a supermassive Galaxy
so that is an interesting question what
is Andromeda Andromeda is our nearest
proper Galaxy we have two other galaxies
that are closer than Andromeda the large
magellanic cloud and the small one but
Andromeda is the proper galact proper
Galaxy that is the closest neighbor to
our own galaxy The Milky Way so
andromedia is about two and a half
million light years away from here
and what we know
is that if we examine the light that
comes from this galaxy it is not red
shifted it is blue shifted which tells
you that it is coming towards us
at a certain speed
so the Andromeda galaxy all other
galaxies that we see are red shifted
because of the expansion of the universe
which means they are moving further away
from us and this expansion is
accelerating
but Andromeda is so close to us only two
and a half
or so million light years away that the
force of gravity between Andromeda and
the Milky Way
is greater than the force caused by the
expansion of the universe that's why
these two objects these two galaxies are
coming closer together they are moving
closer together and eventually Andromeda
and Milky Way the two galaxies our home
Galaxy and our neighbor are going to
collide well it's not really a collision
it's a merger so it's going to be a
gravitational dance they will come
together they will pass through each
other
starts will be flung in all directions
some Stars may be flung so so rapidly
aware that they will be gone forever but
eventually after a few so this Collision
or merger will happen in about four and
a half billion years from now
and that entire process will likely last
two three maybe four maybe five billion
years this entire Galactic tango dance
and eventually what would emerge from
this is a larger Galaxy some Stars will
be flung off gone forever but eventually
the two galaxies will merge together and
give rise to a larger much larger Galaxy
that will be approximately
the mass of Galaxy a and Galaxy B put
together approximately slightly less
so that's what it is so it's not going
to be a collision it's going to be a
merger why no Collision because if you
look at space it's mostly empty and the
distance the average distance between
any two stars in the Milky Way or
Andromeda is so vast
that the even when the two objects come
together there's no not going to be a
single most likely there's going to be
no Collision of any two stars it's just
going to be a gravitational dance
so that's what's going to happen that is
the answer the two galaxies will not
Collide they will merge together to form
a more massive Galaxy I would not call
it a supermassive Galaxy but um much a
larger Galaxy which will roughly be the
sum of the masses of the two galaxies
Alpha Beta says what kind of fuel will
be the will be best to use for straight
for space travel
so as of today the best fuel that we
have is uh chemical fuel chemical
Rockets
um whichever has the best specific
impulse so if you look at aviation fuel
jet fuel it's typically kerosene it's uh
specific impulse isn't that great if you
take the uh
the fuel that you use in chemical
Rockets
it's typically uh you have different
kinds of fuels you have hydrogen and
oxygen you have hydrogen peroxide you
have hypergolic fuels and a whole
various classes of fuels there are solid
fuels liquid fuels and whatnot the
simplest fuel you can imagine for space
travel as of today is liquid hydrogen
and liquid oxygen you bring them
together they will ignite give off H2O
with a huge amount of energy
uh that goes downwards and which will
push the rocket in the opposite
direction
so that is typically what we use and of
course we have like I said a variety of
different fuels as well
so these are all chemical fuels
and that's what we use today for space
travel that is
very primitive
if I was an alien who travels across
galaxies I would laugh at these
primitive little monkeys who are using
chemical Rockets What would Advanced
aliens use foreign for example
if I were to speculate
I would say that they would use
the reaction
of matter and antimatter
together
so antimatter and matter if you bring
them together they just annihilate and
give off your energy vast amounts of
energy E equals Mt squared right
so I think that could if you can
actually harness macro antimatter bring
them together in a controlled manner if
you can store antimatter in a in a way
that doesn't annihilate it
so that will require very Advanced
Technology Way Beyond anything that we
have first of all we we don't even have
the means of producing any reasonable
amount of antimatter the most amount of
antimatter we can produce or store is
just
um maybe microgram or something
milligrams perhaps
and to store antimattery we need the
magnetic confinement
so uh advanced technology if aliens have
that they would be able to store maybe
kilos or hundreds of kilos of antimatter
together
maybe anti-hydrogen and regular hydrogen
and then bring them together to react in
a combustion chamber and give off Pure
Energy
and that would be an excellent way
excellent fuel for traveling
Interstellar distances Intergalactic
distances perhaps but even that would
not allow you to to breach the speed of
light obviously because of really
relativity because of the laws of
physics so the other thing is we could
possibly in the future have warp drives
so that is a that may actually be
feasible
um possibly but that is very very
speculative and futuristic technology
but it may be possible within the
laws of physics it may be allowed so so
these are some some things so what is
warp drives you actually
warped the fabric of space-time itself
and that impels you through space-time
possibly at speeds that exceed the spare
speed of light but whether because you
are inside a certain bubble of
space-time which itself is moving
through the larger fabric of space time
that's why you're not technically
breaking the laws of physics that sort
of thing so that may happen maybe if we
stick around for another thousand years
maybe maybe shorter hopefully let's see
so that's a bit of speculation about
space travel
more quantum
group says can you discuss quantum
entanglement and what are the current
theories on how this phenomenon happens
quantum entanglement spooky action at a
distance Einstein Rosen and
Rosenberg who was it Einstein two of his
uh Millions students students
collaborators so they came up with this
very interesting idea and it's valid so
what is it what is quantum entanglement
I I can best explain this using an
analogy
let's say I have a pair
of gloves you know what's a glove you
wear it on your hands right let's see I
have a pair of gloves so what I'm gonna
do I take this pair of gloves
I put it on the desk hmm
I close my eyes and I shuffle them
around without looking okay
then I take one glove and put it in a
box a take the other glove and put it in
the Box B without looking at which glove
it is my eyes are closed and I close the
boxes box a and box B and seal them
now box a I send it
to Berlin
and box B I send it send it to Bangalore
I don't know which glove has gone into
box B to Bangalore and which glove has
gone to Berlin now my friend in Berlin
opens the box and sees that it's a
left-handed glove inside
then my friend in Berlin will
instantaneously know that what has gone
to Bangalore is a right-handed glove
corresponding to the left-handed partner
that he has got or she has got right
that is
one way of looking at quantum
entanglement
so now let's take this analogy and put
it into and and apply it to quantum
mechanics
quantum mechanics is all about the
subatomic world the hyper microscopic
world let's say you have a subatomic
particle with spin zero let's not go
into what spin is
particles have SP let's say spin is a
property of a particle
spin up and spin down are the two
allowed states of this quantum number of
spin you can either have spin up or spin
down but a composite particle may have
spin zero
okay so let's say I have a composite
particle Quantum particle which
spontaneously disintegrates into two
daughter particles
so my spin zero particle breaks into two
particles now this daughter particle a
has pinned up in Dota particle B has
pinned down
and if you bring them again together
they will spin zero because up and down
add up to zero
so my Quantum particle breaks into two
particles daughter particles pin up and
spin down particle a goes to Alpha
Centauri our neighboring star a Proxima
Centauri our neighboring star
that's particle a with spin up
in particle B which spin down goes
to the Andromeda galaxy two and a half
million light years away
now my alien friend in Andromeda is
going to detect the particle
and he or she or it will see it's a spin
zero or spin down
and then even though
he or it is two and a half million light
years away from particle a which has pin
up he will instantaneously know by
measuring one particle what the state of
the other particle is
this seems to break
the speed of light
because for information to travel from
Two and a half million light years away
would take a time period of two and a
half million years and yet
the alien friend of mine in Andromeda
knows instantaneously
what the particle at the other end
of that distance is
so that is an entangled system
an entangled system from the quantum
mechanical definition is
a composite system of of two or more
particles that has the same wave
function so this system of particles
cannot be
[Music]
can be described
to describe the system of particles you
need a single wave function and they are
intrinsically entangled together there
is no way of telling of of describing
one particle
without also describing the other
particle
that's one way of putting it the best
way of doing it is through equations but
I don't want to do that because it won't
make sense to you
so that's what it is it's a system that
whose properties are entangled
together
so if You observe if you detect and
measure one particle and see what state
it is in you will immediately know what
the state of the other particle is and
this is something that has been tested
or kilometers you have satellites in
orbit that are able to uh test
and validate that entanglement does
happen at large distances
so that is what quantum entanglement is
and that's how it happens in in well
roughly approximately
right
um
animesh says what is your take on some
mystery spots that claim to defy gravity
there are three four places in the U.S
and a few more in Russia are these
artificially created with optical
illusion or can there actually be some
effect of high magnetic fields and
gravitational force gravity gravitation
and the magnetic force are totally
separate
magnetism has no effect on gravity
now
um yeah there are there are these places
called Magnetic Hill or whatever even in
India right somewhere in Northern India
in ladakh or something there is a place
called Magnetic Hill where Vehicles
apparently go upwards instead of down
and all that these are nothing but
optical illusions
none of these can be proven
scientifically to defy gravity
it's nice illusions that you see it's it
all depends on the camera angle you
angle the camera in a certain way things
will look like they're going up
so that's what it is and sometimes even
if you're there in person based on where
you're standing and all that it may look
like things are going up even if you
have switched off the motor or whatever
you know it's just illusions
there is no such thing as the effect of
magnetism on gravity
magnetic fields do not affect the
gravitational force gravitation is not a
force it's it's geometro Dynamics it's
the effect of Mass on space time and
vice versa
so the presence of mass mass tells
space-time how to curve and the
curvature of space-time tells Mass how
to move that is general relativity and
that is what we perceive this curvature
of space-time
this curvature of four dimensional space
time that we are enmeshed in that's what
we perceive as the force of gravity so
there are no mystery spots that really
defy gravity they appear to because of
optical illusions and all that I think
it's nothing more than that
Suga says are
um do the laws of physics remain the
same in the entire universe or do they
change from Galaxy to Galaxy well I have
only seen what I can see from my
perspective on this Little Rock in my
Galaxy
all the data that we have is from our
Vantage Point here on this planet in our
galaxy and from all the data that we
have collected over all the centuries
and whatever
the laws of physics seem to be the same
everywhere
so that is the brief answer the from
science is about data it's about
observations and from all the
observations that we have the laws of
physics seem to remain the same in all
directions and all distances
there is your answer sir
Christoph friction says in one of the
previous episodes you mentioned that you
only have one meal per day all you can
eat style what is the science behind
that is it actually a good idea to mix
carbs with protein I heard it's not
ideal to eat fruits with dairy dairy
milk or legumes for instance wouldn't it
be better to
take a have a break between eating
different kinds of food okay
uh first of all is there any yeah I do
eat typically one meal a day when I'm
traveling Etc it's not always possible
to do that but when I'm not traveling
when I'm at home when I can control
things I prefer to eat one meal a day
all you can eat Style
so one massive meal and that's it done
then forget about food one meal
um what's the science behind this it's
not typically all about science it's
about what works best for you you have
to observe your body You observe the I
have tried six meals a day
micro meals
I have tried intermittent fasting I've
tried all kinds of things and I found
that what works best for me for my
physiology for my DNA for my metabolism
is one meal a day it works good for me
uh I don't gain weight I gain a
reasonable amount of muscle when I'm
working out and all so that works for me
it may not work for you it may not work
for person X it may work even better
than me for person y it depends
everybody is different we are all human
unique
human beings now
is it a good idea to mix carbs and
protein is it not better to eat fruit
separately and dairy separately and this
separately and that separately
look
we are
anatomically genetically the same as our
ancestors who lived a hundred thousand
years ago one lakh years ago
one hundred thousand years ago
our ancestors were most likely
hunter-gatherers
when you are a hunter-gatherer
you hunt
and if you're lucky you get a get get
you kill some animal rabbit or or a
giraffe or whatever it is
and when you do that you and your family
or you and your tribe your community
enjoy a big meal
then is Go Back to Basics go back to
hunting you may go several days without
getting lucky in your hunt
those days you don't eat
sometimes you may find some fruits you
may find some root vegetables whatever
that was the hunter-gatherer gatherer
lifestyle that is still encoded in our
DNA
we have not changed a hundred thousand
years is not enough for evolution to to
make itself known so the human species
Homo sapiens has been the same for at
least a quarter of a million years 250
000 years ago two and a half lakh years
anatomically the same genetically we
also more or less the same we have not
changed much in the time so all of that
that lifestyle the hunter-gatherer
feasting and fasting lifestyle is still
encoded in our DNA
so when our ancestors would hunt they
would Feast they would eat carbs they
would if they found fruits whatever they
found they would eat at the same time
there were no refrigerators at the time
there was no storage there were no there
was no agriculture
no grain storage so you found a few
potatoes you found a few onions and you
found a rabbit you ate all of that at
the same time and it worked perfectly
fine for us so all of this new fangled
so-called science Bro Science that you
should eat fruit separately don't mix
carbs and fat so don't mix carbs and
protein all of that stuff doesn't make
sense
whatever lifestyle was our ancestors you
used to follow we can still follow it
today and be in good health one of the
best rules of thumb
when it comes to deciding what to eat is
to ask yourself a simple question
did our ancestors didn't forget about
ancestors did human beings eat this
a thousand years ago
you go to McDonald's whatever you find
there nobody ate there a thousand years
ago so don't eat that it's unhealthy
you go to a pizzeria
did anybody eat pizza with all the
toppings and all that a thousand years
ago no nobody did so don't eat that it's
not healthy for you
some people like to drink wine yeah wine
has been around for thousands of years
so yeah you can drink a little bit as
long as you don't bring in Access so the
simple rule of thumb is if they did not
eat it a thousand years ago don't eat it
today it's not healthy for you all of
this processed food all the stuff that
people eat these days that's why you
have this obesity obesity epidemic
diabetes
coronary heart disease and God knows
what are the things it's all because of
processed food and all that
if you can cut that out eat unprocessed
Foods lots of vegetables whatever
protein works for you
Etc you'll be just fine
so that's what I can say from my
personal experience
right
um
alphabet Alpha Beta is lucky today
what is sleeping paralysis paralysis is
it really related to horror or
paranormal is there any permanent cure
it's called sleep paralysis it's a I
don't know what so it's it's a
it is something many people experience
apparently
in which you're asleep and then you wake
up but you are paralyzed you are not
able to move
and you feel like there is some
Supernatural presence in the dark room
that you are in the middle of the night
typically and you feel that there is
something sitting on your chest
something heavy and you're unable to
breathe
so it feels like there's some Demon or
something sitting on your chest you
can't move your muscles you can't open
your eyes and it's frightening and this
is something that people experience many
people apparently experience at least
once in their life
so that is a phenomenon called sleep
paralysis it seems to be some sort of
neurological or psychological phenomenon
it's something that is known to happen
so it is nothing to do with horror or
paranormal stuff or whatever because
those things that that well
have you ever seen a ghost
so the thing is this uh it seems to be a
neurological or or psychological
phenomenon ghosts don't exist from this
perspective of science because you can't
take a photograph of a coach you can you
can replicate the phenomenon of ghosts
in paranormal so let's uh keep that out
of the image you know
so that is what sleep paralysis is it is
a frightening thing I believe people who
experience this uh find it a very
scary frightening experience they feel
like yeah we have experienced the
Paranormal the supernatural we've
experienced a ghost or demon or
something that's what they feel like
uh
I don't know about permanent cures or
anything or if even if there is any cure
I think it happens to people who sleep
on their back
so typically when you're sleeping on
your back you feel that there is
something sitting on your chest right
here
so possibly one of the cures would be
one of the if somebody experiences this
on a regular basis maybe you can sleep
on your side instead of sleeping on your
on your back or sleep on your on your
face on the stomach
so maybe that could help so that's what
I can say about this thing
Arman says how can an average person who
doesn't have scientific training tell if
a research paper is credible or not
there is no
way to sugarcoat this a person who
doesn't have scientific training cannot
tell if a research paper is credible or
not the only thing you can do if you
don't have scientific training is to
rely on the opinions
of people who do have scientific
training but then it is like second-hand
opinion that you are that you're
imbibing
so when you are relying on opinions
you're always uh
opinions are always unreliable
many scientists have opinions that have
been that have turned out to be
completely wrong and many scientific
papers high quality scientific papers
so so one of the um
one of the criteria that people
typically use as a benchmark is to see
whether a scientific paper has been
published in a peer-reviewed journal so
that is one Benchmark the second
Benchmark is does it have lots of
citations do lots of other scientists
cite that paper in that case it is very
credible right
in some scientific papers are not
published in peer-reviewed journals some
scientific papers are are just left out
there as preprints
there is this very famous
preprint server called archive archive
arxiv.org which is the preprint
repository for the physical sciences for
computer science mathematics and so on
so forth
you know what
when the very
famous
mathematician Gregory pelerman
came up with his proof of the puancare
conjecture
he wrote it down in a paper in the form
of a paper
and he simply placed it
on the preprint archive he did not
submit it for publication
to any pre-reviewed paper 220
peer-reviewed Journal
so his
groundbreaking proof of the poconic
conjecture
was placed on a pre-print server and it
was not peer reviewed
so that's also what you get so it
doesn't mean that if somebody has simply
put the research on a p on a preprint
server it doesn't mean it's not credible
one of the greatest mathematical
breakthroughs of all time was never
peer-reviewed and
what happened after that is a bunch of
Chinese scientists tried to steal that
and try to trig take the credit for for
the solving of the
conjecture they tried to steal credit
from Gregory Perlman so that's what
happened so the so at the end of the day
there is no way for
um person without scientific training to
really tell
whether a research paper is credible or
not but there are these benchmarks that
you can follow and that would give you a
good idea of how good or bad a paper may
be if it is published
that's a that's a good good sign if it
has lots of citations it's an even
better sign
so that's how you can possibly guess
whether it's credible or not
okay this is big Aditya says I have
recently joined the IIT an IIT GE
coaching Institute in the 10th standard
I had simple topics like linear
quadratic equations linear equations
Pythagoras Theorem uh various
progressions and so on I was good at
math I used to get 80 out of 80 marks
but on the first day of coaching that
taught us uh differential and integral
calculus I found it very difficult dydx
d square y by DX squared my confidence
is has suddenly gone down I used to be a
Topper but now I'm feeling that I'll
become the lowermost student of maths
the same thing is happening for
chemistry physics Etc
please guide me and how to do study of
chemistry
look the first time somebody encounters
calculus it's like you're suddenly
thrown into the ocean it's so different
from everything you've been taught
before
differentiation integration differential
equations and so on and so forth It's
like scary the first time you encounter
it it's like your whole world whatever
you you thought was was the reality all
of it has suddenly turned out to be
illusion that's how you typically feel
the first time you encounter calculus
different differential differentiation
integration and so on typically
one finds integration harder than
differentiation because it's the
opposite of that and it's got a whole
toolkit of techniques that we must learn
so what do you do
simple
solve
problems
take
a book of problems of calculus first of
all what you do the first thing you do
is you try and understand the concepts
what is differentiation what do you mean
by d y by DX what are limits get these
Basics right
talk to a good teacher if you have one
or acquire a good book the Sham series
books on pre-calculus calculus are
excellent they're excellent for
self-study so first understand these
Concepts properly there are lots of
YouTube videos which I believe would
give excellent uh excellent uh
um expositions on on these basic
concepts so first get the concepts right
geometrically
what does d y by DX mean what does an
integral mean from a from the geometric
perspective understand that get the
concept right then
what you do is you solve problems not
two problems not 12 problems you solve
hundreds and hundreds of problems you go
through it you force yourself for days
weeks months give you some three months
just solve a hundred problems per day
maybe more if you have the time go
through it do it again and again and
again until it becomes second nature you
do this I guarantee you it will become
the easiest thing in the world
differentiation then the same thing for
integration
solve hundreds of problems 100 problems
a day solve 100 integrals per day do it
for three months see what happens your
confidence at the end of those three
months will be Sky High same for
differential equations and everything
else
you have to put in the hard work there
is no substitute for hard work
you have to put in the hundreds of hours
and you know solve the thousands of
problems you do that I guarantee
that you will become the Topper Again
and the same goes for chemistry you have
to solve problems get the concepts the
fundamentals right very very
you have to be crystal clear about the
fundamentals and then solve hundreds of
problems to be a good student to be good
at anything in life
you have to put in the hard work there
is no substitute for Hard Work Talent is
overrated Talent means nothing you might
be the most gifted and intelligent
person but if you will not put in the
hard work you will you will achieve
nothing so that's what I would tell you
all the best Aditya
um
okay AKB was from Mumbai I love science
especially physics Aerospace Etc I'm
very passionate about science but
recently I scored only 57 percent in the
12th boards I cannot understand why I
can't do better in exams I don't like
root learning over the years my whole
YouTube feed consists of lectures from
Brian Greene Lawrence Krauss Michio Kaku
feinman and your videos my videos even
being so passionate about it I cannot
score in the subjects should I leave
science as I've been told by many or
should I stick to it as it's my passion
I would say that the when it comes to
passing exams
it's again about
going through the process of solving
hundreds of problems rote learning is a
pain I know but in the Indian education
system you want to get good marks you
may have to indulge in some rooting
learning so once again the solution the
the answer is the same
you there is no substitute for hard work
you have to solve hundreds of problems
you have to put in hundreds you to solve
thousands of problems you have to put in
hundreds of hours of hard work effort
you do that you will become good at
anything
but of course it's also about aptitude
you may love science you may be
passionate about it but maybe for
whatever reason you may be better at
something else in in actual practice as
a practitioner
some people love music but they can
never play good music
right it doesn't mean that they should
not enjoy music but it means that they
should enjoy music as a hobby as a
listener as a consumer
but as a practitioner they should pick
up some other career that is also a
possibility so you may be somebody who
loves science who's passionate about it
pursue that as a hobby pursue that as a
consumer of contempt but maybe as a
practitioner you may be better at some
other some other occupation that is also
a possibility so try approach a first do
the hard work
solve hundreds thousands of problems
put in the dedication and the in the
effort for
three to six months and see what the
results are and if you still don't find
any Improvement in your marks then maybe
you should take up after after putting
after doing this this uh experiment if
it still doesn't work then maybe you
should take up something else so give
yourself a chance first and put in the
hard work and if you still feel that
you're not doing well enough then maybe
you can pursue science as a hobby and
take up some other occupation okay so
that's what I can say
have both plants ready
okay let's take a couple more questions
this is by samhita is microbial life
present on Mars
does that somehow give give a hint of
possible existence of Life of life
Life on Mars millions of years ago so we
don't have unambiguous evidence of
microbial life having existed on Mars
we have a piece of rock I forgot what is
called alh something something
uh we know it came from Mars
and a cross section of this rock was
taken and microscopic analysis was done
and what was detected is microtubules
that look exactly like the like the
capsules of bacteria on Earth
so if it is indeed the the fossilized
remains of ancient bacteria then it
means that in the past there used to be
bacteria on Mars maybe even today they
may have survived underground possibly
so it's a possibility but it's not 100
proven
some people say it's just just a
coincidence some scientists say it could
be just a coincidence it is not
an unambiguous demonstration that this
represents ancient life or or a sign of
ancient life uh apart from that
we have certain the Americans NASA has
uh as a Rover I forgot what it's called
perseverance Ingenuity endurance
whatever it's called
so it's it's doing some research there
there's a helicopter also over there a
small rotor craft
so but that's not quite equipped to to
look for signs of life it's doing
various kinds of scientific tests on the
atmosphere and the soil and the
composition of rocks and all that but
that's not enough to tell us
uh for sure whether life existed or not
we do know
that a couple of billion years ago there
was flowing water on Mars Mars was a
much hotter place it had a much thicker
atmosphere it had a magnetic field and
it's quite likely it not likely it's
quite possible it is not quite possible
it is possible that life may have
existed on Mars at that time when it was
a nice warm planet with a thicker
atmosphere and flowing water it's
possible
so the possibility is very much there
but the evidence still is not there with
us at least unambiguous evidence
uh we don't have that
right so that's the answer
The Logical motivation 95 says can you
explain the spaghetti effect in detail
and in normal English please well that's
what I strive to do I try to I strive to
explain things in normal language
so
have you seen Saturn
so what you're talking about the
spaghetti effect is called
spaghettification it is something that
is related to Black Hole so let me
explain this
we know the the very famous iconic
planet called Saturn Saturn has rings
it's a planet a gas giant with a massive
ring system around it why do those Rings
exist
those rings are the debris the rubble
that comes out of an ancient moon of
Saturn that was destroyed maybe in a
collision or something else now in
physics in classical Newtonian physics
there is something called the Roche
limit
r-o-c-h-e Roche limit in the rosh effect
that has something to do with tidal
forces so
every Mass every object every planet has
a Roche limit so this limit is the limit
at which
if any orbiting object
comes within that limit it is going to
be ripped apart by tidal forces and it
won't be able to stay in one piece
roughly that's what it means roughly
okay no this is not the precise
definition but if the moon for instance
if the Earth's moon were to come closer
to the Earth this is the Earth this is
the moon if we were to move the moon
much closer and bring it within the
Roche limit
then the moon would be disintegrated by
the by the tidal force of the earth what
does tidal force mean it means the Earth
is here and let's say this is a
satellite the pull of gravity on the
part of the object that is closer to the
Earth
is way greater than the pull of gravity
on the other part and that distorts and
and destroys the object that is the
tidal Force at the Roche limit and and
within that
so in the case of a black hole
the force of gravity as you go close at
what black hole is way way stronger
black holes have incredibly strong
gravity
so as you come closer and closer to the
event horizon of a black hole the tidal
Force
becomes larger
so let's say you're a human being let's
say this is a human being going towards
a black hole the bottom of the screen is
towards a black hole you're going closer
and closer and as you go closer to the
black hole the force of gravity on the
legs
is way greater than the force of gravity
on the head of the person and we know
what that does it'll pull that person
and stretch that person apart like like
strands of spaghetti so that is
spaghettification
and as you cross the Event Horizon and
go towards the singularity which may be
there inside the tidal Force gets even
stronger
so
so if it is a reasonably small black
hole this spaghettification is much
larger much much stronger and the tidal
forces are much much greater if it's a
supermassive black hole you may not
experience that drastic
um spaghetti effect so that in short
in brief in normal English is
pagetification it's that a person who is
falling into into a black hole feet
first or head first will be pulled apart
as if they are spaghetti
not a not a good way to go right so that
is the spaghetti effect all right I am
done with today's questions
shall I take a couple of
live chat questions
okay can we drink alcohol in black hole
well if you can get inside a black hole
with your bottle of alcohol you can try
it
okay what else do we have
um
let's take a couple of questions
um if we can
you have some questions I'll take a
couple now
ISRO me Venus Mission I have heard of
some mission that ISRO is supposed to do
undertake to Venus
is it called I'm not sure
so I don't know the details I don't know
which year is going to happen maybe by
2025 or something that was the that's
what I had heard a couple of years ago
so typically what one would imagine is
that um
you would send a spacecraft to this
planet to our neighboring planet Venus
the spacecraft would go into orbit
around Venus and it would have a bunch
of scientific instruments that would uh
do various
tests and Analysis of the atmosphere and
maybe the surface of the parent so if
you send the spacecraft that has a radar
or with it then you can maybe do a radar
uh scan of the surface of the planet and
uh get details about its topology
and if you have spectrometers and other
things then you can look at the
composition of the gases of the
atmosphere and gain more knowledge about
that so that's the kind of thing you
could do
in a Venus mission mission and that's
possibly what the shukrayan mission will
be about but I'm not sure when it's
going to be launched and so that is
still something that needs to be looked
at
all right um
you would take the diet question but not
mine you are a typical Indian
I am a typical Indian sir but I don't
know what your question is instead of
asking this question or making this
comment you're going to ask your
question again I get thousands of
comments I cannot pick everybody's
question please understand that please
okay what else do we have okay some
people asking questions about
things that are not related to science
please don't do that today is about
science
this live stream is only about science
uh when is the Earth going to be
destroyed the Earth will be destroyed
when our sun
becomes a red giant
so in roughly about five billion years
from today
the sun will become larger and larger it
will have become a red giant and
eventually it will shed its outer layers
and that will go out in the form of a
nebula uh planetary nebula like like
which may look kind of like
the Cat's Eye Nebula perhaps
the sun is never going to go supernova
the sun is too small for that
so it will eventually shed its outer
layers it will first become a red giant
it may engulf the planet Mercury
within its within itself when it becomes
a red giant and eventually the nuclear
reaction within the Sun at the core will
become weaker and uh
and the outer layers will be expelled
slowly over time and that could very
much destroy the Earth
and be even before that when the sun
becomes a red giant the oceans will boil
off and whatever water is left on the
planet will disappear the planet Earth
will become very hot and dry
so that's the kind of Destruction our
planet will see eventually the sun will
become
a white dwarf and
spend its days it's its remaining days
like that
so that is the kind of Fate eventual
long-term fate our planet will see
foreign
what is Murphy's Law is it purely
hypothetical Murphy's Law is not science
Murphy's law says that if something can
go wrong it will go wrong
it's not science it's just a it's kind
of a joke actually it's not a joke
actually it's quite painful people
experience that
but it is not science it is it is
a certain pattern that one sees in life
sometimes
that if something can go wrong
it probably will go wrong unless you
have taken the best of precautions so
that is what Murphy's Law is and that's
where we are
do I believe in ghosts well I have not
seen a ghost so unless I see one how do
I believe in it
yeah but I don't know if I mean
ghosts are something you can't prove or
disprove so that's not science it's
philosophy or spirituality or whatever
all right I think we are at the end of
today's session almost two hours
almost two hours so we'll we'll end it
here thank you everybody great to be
talking science again that is what I
mean that's what I find the most
interesting I'm a Science Guy more than
a history guy or a geopolitist guy or
whatever else guy science is what I
enjoy the most so it was great to do
this again and we'll do it again in the
future
thank you everybody for your questions
thank you for watching thank you for
your viewership and once again this
video was sponsored by the like button
go and smash it and thank our sponsors
thank you very much
and I will see you in the next
live stream which is tomorrow bye